Guide to the Foster and Company Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Foster and Company records
1836-1890
MS 1403
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(20 boxes)
The records consist of account books, cashbooks, invoice books, journals, ledgers, and letterbooks documenting the business transactions of Foster and Company, a retail and wholesale grocery in Hartford, Connecticut.
Foster and Company
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Armstrong, 1943.
Arrangement
Arranged in eight sections: Accounts, 1839-1863; Cashbooks, 1836-1890; Ham Book, 1861-1867; Invoice Books, 1836-1864; Journals, 1840-1861; Ledgers, 1836-1869; Letterbooks, 1836-1866; and Oversize, 1852-1868.
Scope and Contents
The Foster and Company Records consist of cashbooks, invoice books, journals, ledgers, other account books, and letterbooks which document the business transactions of a retail and wholesale grocer in Hartford, Connecticut. The records date from 1836 until 1890 but the bulk of the material dates before 1865. The records include accounts for Foster and Hosford (1836-1837) and James P. Foster (1837-1839), predecessor firms to Foster and Company. The firm was run as Foster and Co. by James Phelps Foster and his brother Ralph Henry Foster and, after 1880, by James Phelps Foster's three sons.
The records are arranged by record type and include an extensive, though incomplete, set of the standard general ledgers and journals which characterize double entry bookkeeping. There are also nine volumes of cashbooks, which detail cash expenditures and income and seven volumes of invoice books which record wholesale purchases. The invoice books also contain annual inventories of stock and net worth; the 1839 value of the company was $5,238, while the 1862 inventory lists this total as $12,787. Other volumes include accounts of bills payable and receivable, charges by Wells and Burnham and Bell and Baldwin for carting, a journal of Ralph Rose Foster, and a "Ham Book", which details purchases of ham, lard, pork, apples, and cider. Two letterbooks contain copies of out-going letters concerning purchases for the store and other details of its operation.
The library purchased the records of Foster and Company in 1943 from Armstrong. The records were transferred from the Account Books Collection (MS 29) in 1985.
Biographical / Historical
The business began operation under the name Foster and Hosford, and changed its name to James P. Foster (1837-1839). The firm then became Foster and Company for the remainder of the time documented in the records. James Phelps Foster (1800-1878) and his brother Ralph Henry Foster (d. 1877) headed the business in 1842. Three sons of James Phelps Foster, Frederick Rose Foster (b. 1827), James Phelps Foster, Jr., and George Bushnell Foster operated the business after 1880.
Business; Grocery trade; Connecticut -- Commerce; Hartford (Conn.) -- Commerce; Account books; Ledgers; Foster, James Phelps, 1800-1878; Foster family; Foster and Company
- Inventory, 1836-1890
  - Accounts
    - Bills payable and receivable, 1839-1854 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      See also: box 20, folder 50
    - Cartage accounts with Wells & Burnham and Bell & Baldwin, 1853-1854, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Cashbooks
    - [A], 1836-1840 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - B, 1840-1842 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - C, 1842-1845 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - [D], 1845-1848 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - [E], 1848-1854 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - [F], 1853-1856 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - J, 1860-1862 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - K, 1862-1864 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - L, 1864-1890 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Ham Book, 1861-1867 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Invoice Books
    - A, 1836-1841 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - B, 1841-1846 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - C, 1846-1849 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - D, 1850-1853 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - E, 1853-1858 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - F, 1858-1862 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - G, 1861-1864 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Journals
    - C, 1840-1841 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - D, 1841-1843 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - E, 1843-1844 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - F, 1844-1845 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - G, 1845-1846 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - J, 1848-1849 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - K, 1849-1850 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - L, 1850-1851 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - M, 1851-1852 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - O, 1853-1854 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - P, 1854-1855 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Q, 1855-1856 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - R, 1856-1857 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - S, 1857-1858 (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - U, 1859 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - W, 1860-1861 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Foster, Ralph Rose, 1860-1862 (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - AA, 1862-1863 (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - BB, 1863 (Box 16, Folder 39)
    - DD, 1864 (Box 16, Folder 40)
    - FF, 1865-1866 (Box 17, Folder 41)
  - Ledgers
    - 1836-1844 (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - 1841-1847 (Box 17, Folder 43)
    - 1841-1869 (Box 18, Folder 44)
    - 1860-1865 (Box 18, Folder 45)
      See also: box 20, folders 51-52
  - Letterbooks
    - A, 1836-1847 (Box 19, Folder 46)
    - B, 1856-1858 (Box 19, Folder 47)
    - Financial data, 1844-1845; 1862-1866 (Box 19, Folder 48)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1855 (Box 19, Folder 49)
  - Oversize
    - Accounts, 1852-1861 (Box 20, Folder 50)
      See also: box 1, folder 1
    - Ledger A, 1865-1868 (Box 20, Folder 51)
      Related Materials
      See also: box 17, folders 42-45
    - Ledger H, 1860-1865 (Box 21, Folder 52)